(Applause) Duality is the ability to hold both things. But the question is: Can we own our duality? Can we have the courage to hold both things? I work at a restaurant in town, I became really good friends with the busser. I was a server and we had a great relationship, we had a really great time together. Her Spanish was great because she was from Mexico. (Laughter) That line actually went the other way. Her English was limited, but significantly better than my Spanish. But we were united by our similarities, not separated by our differences. And we were close, even though we came from very different worlds. She was from Mexico, she left her family behind so she could come here and afford them a better life back home. She was a devout conservative Catholic, a believer in traditional family values, stereotypical roles of men and women, and I was, well, me. (Laughter) But the things that bonded us were when she asked about my girlfriend, or she shared pictures that she had from her family back home. Those were the things that brought us together. So one day, we were in the back, scarfing down food as quickly as we could, gathered around a small table, during a very rare lull, and a new guy from the kitchen came over -- who happened to be her cousin -- and sat down with all the bravado and machismo that his 20-year-old body could hold. (Laughter) And he said to her, [in Spanish] "Does Ash have a boyfriend?" And she said, [in Spanish] "No, she has a girlfriend." And he said, [in Spanish] "A girlfriend?!?" And she set down her fork, and locked eyes with him, and said, [in Spanish] "Yes, a girlfriend. That is all." And his smug smile quickly dropped to one of maternal respect, grabbed his plate, walked off, went back to work. She never made eye contact with me. She left, did the same thing -- it was a 10-second conversation, such a short interaction. And on paper, she had so much more in common with him: language, culture, history, family, her community was her lifeline here, but her moral compass trumped all of that. And a little bit later, they were joking around in the kitchen in Spanish, that had nothing to do with me, and that is duality. She didn't have to choose some P.C. stance on gayness over her heritage. She didn't have to choose her family over our friendship. It wasn't Jesus or Ash. (Laughter) (Applause) Her individual morality was so strongly rooted that she had the courage to hold both things. Our moral integrity is our responsibility and we must be prepared to defend it even when it's not convenient. That's what it means to be an ally, and if you're going to be an ally, you have to be an active ally: Ask questions, act when you hear something inappropriate, actually engage. I had a family friend who for years used to call my girlfriend my lover. Really? Lover? So overly sexual, so '70s gay porn. (Laughter) But she was trying, and she asked. She could have called her my friend, or my "friend," or my "special friend" -- (Laughter) -- or even worse, just not asked at all. Believe me, we would rather have you ask. I would rather have her say lover, than say nothing at all. People often say to me, "Well, Ash, I don't care. I don't see race or religion or sexuality. It doesn't matter to me. I don't see it." But I think the opposite of homophobia and racism and xenophobia is not love, it's apathy. If you don't see my gayness, then you don't see me. If it doesn't matter to you who I sleep with, then you cannot imagine what it feels like when I walk down the street late at night holding her hand, and approach a group of people and have to make the decision if I should hang on to it or if I should I drop it when all I want to do is squeeze it tighter. And the small victory I feel when I make it by and don't have to let go. And the incredible cowardice and disappointment I feel when I drop it. If you do not see that struggle that is unique to my human experience because I am gay, then you don't see me. If you are going to be an ally, I need you to see me. As individuals, as allies, as humans, we need to be able to hold both things: both the good and the bad, the easy and the hard. You don't learn how to hold two things just from the fluff, you learn it from the grit. And what if duality is just the first step? What if through compassion and empathy and human interaction we are able to learn to hold two things? And if we can hold two things, we can hold four, and if we can hold four, we can hold eight, and if we can hold eight, we can hold hundreds. We are complex individuals, swirls of contradiction. You are all holding so many things right now. What can you do to hold just a few more? So, back to Toledo, Ohio. I'm at the front of the line, niece on my shoulders, the frazzled clerk calls me Dad. Have you ever been mistaken for the wrong gender? Not even that. Have you ever been called something you are not? Here's what it feels like for me: I am instantly an internal storm of contrasting emotions. I break out into a sweat that is a combination of rage and humiliation, I feel like the entire store is staring at me, and I simultaneously feel invisible. I want to explode in a tirade of fury, and I want to crawl under a rock. And top all of that off with the frustration that I'm wearing an out-of-character tight-fitting purple t-shirt, so this whole store can see my boobs, to make sure this exact same thing doesn't happen. (Laughter) But, despite my best efforts to be seen as the gender I am, it still happens. And I hope with every ounce of my body that no one heard -- not my sister, not my girlfriend, and certainly not my niece. I am accustomed to this familiar hurt, but I will do whatever I need to do to protect the people I love from it. But then I take my niece off my shoulders, and she runs to Elsa and Anna -- the thing she's been waiting so long for -- and all that stuff goes away. All that matters is the smile on her face. And as the 30 seconds we waited two and a half hours for comes to a close we gather up our things, and I lock eyes with the clerk again; and she gives me an apologetic smile and mouths, "I am so sorry!" (Laughter) And her humanity, her willingness to admit her mistake disarms me immediately, then I give her a: "It's okay, it happens. But thanks." And I realize in that moment that I don't have to be either an aunt or an advocate, I can be both. I can live in duality, and I can hold two things. And if I can hold two things in that environment, I can hold so many more things. As my girlfriend and my niece hold hands and skip out the front of the door, I turn to my sister and say, "Was it worth it?" And she said, "Are you kidding me? Did you see the look on her face? This was the greatest day of her life!" (Laughter) "It was worth the two and a half hours in the heat, it was worth the overpriced coloring book that we already had a copy of." (Laughter) "It was even worth you getting called Dad." And for the first time ever in my life, it actually was. Thank you, Boulder. Have a good night. (Applause)
(Aplausos) La dualidad es la capacidad de mantener ambas cosas. Pero la pregunta es: ¿Podemos poseer nuestra dualidad? ¿Podemos tener el coraje de mantener ambas cosas? Yo trabajé en un restaurante de la ciudad. Me hice muy amiga de una camarera. Yo era la maître y tuvimos una gran relación, nos lo pasamos muy bien juntas. Su español era genial porque ella era de México. (Risas) Eso era también en sentido inverso. Su inglés era limitado, pero significativamente mejor que mi español. Pero estábamos unidas por nuestras similitudes, no separadas por nuestras diferencias. Y estábamos cerca, a pesar ser de mundos muy diferentes. Ella era de México, dejó a su familia para poder venir aquí y darles una mejor vida. Ella era una católica devota conservadora, creyente en los valores tradicionales de la familia, funciones estereotipadas de hombres y mujeres, y yo era, pues yo. (Risas) Lo que nos unía era cuando me preguntaba por mi novia, o cuando compartía fotos de su familia. Eran las cosas que nos unían. Un día estábamos en la parte de atrás, engullendo tan rápido como podíamos, alrededor de una pequeña mesa, durante una pausa muy rara, y vino un chico nuevo de la cocina, resultó ser su primo, y se sentó con toda la osadía y el machismo que sus 20 años podían contener en su cuerpo. (Risas) Y le dijo: [en español] "¿Ash tiene novio?" Y ella dijo: [en español] "No, tiene novia". Y él dijo: [en español] "¡¿Una novia?!" Y ella dejó el tenedor, y le clavó los ojos, y dijo: [en español] "Sí, una novia. Eso es todo". Y su sonrisa de suficiencia cambió rápidamente a una de respeto materno, tomó su plato, se marchó, volvió a trabajar. Ella nunca hizo contacto visual conmigo. Ella se fue, hizo lo mismo... fueron 10 seg. de conversación, con poca interacción. Y en el papel, ella tenía mucho más en común con él: lengua, cultura, historia, familia y su comunidad era su tabla de salvación aquí, pero su brújula moral triunfó sobre todo eso. Y un poco más tarde, bromeaban en la cocina en español, sobre algo que no tenía nada que ver conmigo, y "eso" es la dualidad. No tenía que elegir entre una postura sobre la homosexualidad y su herencia. Ella no tenía que elegir entre su familia y nuestra amistad. Ni entre Jesús o Ash. (Risas) (Aplausos) Su moral individual estaba tan fuertemente arraigada que tuvo el coraje de mantener ambas cosas. Nuestra integridad moral es nuestra responsabilidad y debemos estar preparados para defenderla, incluso si no es conveniente. Eso es lo que significa ser aliado, y si van a ser un aliado, tienen que ser un aliado activo: Hagan preguntas, actúen al escuchar algo inapropiado, realmente participen. Yo tenía una amiga de la familia que por años llamó a mi novia mi "amante". ¿En serio? ¿Amante? Así excesivamente sexual, como los porno gay de los 70. (Risas) Pero ella lo intentó y me preguntó. podría haberla llamado mi "amiga", o "amiga", o mi "amiga especial" (Risas) o peor aún, no haber preguntado nada. Créanme, preferimos que se nos pregunte. Yo preferiría que la llamara mi amante a que no dijera nada en absoluto. La gente a menudo me dice: "Ash, no me importa. No veo la raza ni la religión ni la sexualidad. No me importa. Yo no lo veo". Pero creo que lo contrario de homofobia, racismo y xenofobia no es amor, es apatía. Si no ven mi homosexualidad, entonces no me ven. Si no les importa con quien me acuesto, entonces no se pueden imaginar lo que se siente cuando camino por la calle tarde en la noche, sosteniendo su mano, y acercarse a un grupo de personas y tener que tomar la decisión de si debo aferrarme a ella o si debo soltarla cuando lo único que quiero hacer es apretarla con más fuerza. Y la pequeña victoria que siento cuando lo hago y no tengo que soltarla. Y la cobardía increíble y decepción que siento cuando la suelto. Si no ven esta lucha única en mi experiencia humana por ser gay, entonces no me ven. Si Uds. van a ser aliados, necesito que me vean. Como personas, como aliados, como seres humanos, debemos poder mantener ambas cosas: tanto lo bueno como lo malo, lo fácil y lo difícil. No se aprende a sostener dos cosas desde la tibieza, se aprende desde la firmeza. ¿Y si la dualidad es solo el primer paso? ¿Qué pasa si a través de la compasión, la empatía y la interacción humana podemos aprender a sostener 2 cosas? Y si podemos sostener 2 cosas, podemos sostener 4, y si podemos sostener 4, podemos sostener 8, y si podemos sostener 8, podemos sostener cientos. Somos individuos complejos, remolinos de contradicción. Todos Uds. sostienen muchas cosas en este momento. ¿Qué se puede hacer para mantener un poco más? Así que, volviendo a Toledo, Ohio. Estoy en el frente de la fila, mi sobrina en mis hombros, la empleada agotada me llama papá. ¿Alguna vez les han acreditado con el género equivocado? Ni siquiera eso. ¿Alguna vez les han tildado de algo que no son? Esto es lo que yo siento ante eso: Al instante soy una tormenta interna de emociones enfrentadas. Rompo a sudar en una combinación de rabia y humillación, siento cómo toda la tienda me está mirando, y al mismo tiempo me siento invisible. Quiero explotar en una diatriba de furia, y quiero esconderme debajo de una roca. Y encima de todo eso, con la frustración por usar una ajustada camiseta púrpura donde toda esta tienda puede verme las tetas, para asegurarme de que esto mismo no debe suceder. (Risas) Pero, a pesar de mis mejores esfuerzos para que me vean con el género que soy, todavía sucede. Y espero con cada kg de mi cuerpo que nadie lo oyera, ni mi hermana, ni mi novia, y mucho menos mi sobrina. Estoy acostumbrada a esta herida familiar, pero haré lo que tengo que hacer para proteger a la gente que quiero. Pero luego bajé a mi sobrina de los hombros, y ella corrió hacia Elsa y Anna por lo que había esperado tanto tiempo, y todo eso se me pasa. Lo único que importa es la sonrisa en su rostro. Y cuando faltaban 30 seg. de las dos horas y media de espera recogimos nuestras cosas e intercambié de nuevo una mirada con la empleada; y ella me dio una sonrisa de disculpa y murmuró: "¡Lo siento!" (Risas) Y su humanidad, su voluntad de admitir su error me desarmó inmediatamente, entonces yo: "Está bien, pasa, pero gracias". Y me doy cuenta en ese momento de que ya no tengo que ser o una tía o una militante, que pueden ser ambas a la vez. Puedo vivir en la dualidad, y puedo ser dos cosas. Y si puedo ser dos cosas en ese medio, y puedo sostener tantas cosas más. Cuando mi novia y mi sobrina se van de la mano por la puerta delantera, me dirijo a mi hermana y le digo: "¿Valió la pena?" Y ella dijo: "¿Estás bromeando? ¿Has visto la expresión de su cara? ¡Fue el mejor día de su vida! " (Risas) "Valió la pena las dos horas y media en el calor, valió la pena el libro caro del que ya teníamos una copia". (Risas) "Incluso valió la pena que te llamaran papá". Y por primera vez en mi vida, así fue. Gracias, Boulder. Que tengan una buena noche. (Aplausos)